<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.5.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4444/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4444/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-07-23T10:25:03+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/</id><title type="html">Opinions &amp;amp; Experiments</title><subtitle>Structured and unstructure thoughts. Often IoT-related. Sometimes education-related. By Boris Adryan.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Designing the User Experience of Machine Learning Systems</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/12/04/designing-the-user-experience-of-machine-learning-systems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the User Experience of Machine Learning Systems" /><published>2016-12-04T18:31:06+01:00</published><updated>2016-12-04T18:31:06+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/12/04/designing-the-user-experience-of-machine-learning-systems</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/12/04/designing-the-user-experience-of-machine-learning-systems.html">&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I submitted an abstract to a UX conference. I’m not sure if my proposal is going to be accepted, but I thought it would be worth sharing my thoughts on the user experience of Machine Learning Systems on my currently quite neglected blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BorisAdryan&quot;&gt;@BorisAdryan&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter may have heard about my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingmonk.com&quot;&gt;Thingmonk&lt;/a&gt; talk about that very subject:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OUlgsle6UpM&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan/thingmonk-2015&quot;&gt;slides for my talk&lt;/a&gt; are pretty self-explanatory, the following abstract delivers my motivation a bit more systematically.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;designing-the-user-experience-of-machine-learning-systems&quot;&gt;Designing the User Experience of Machine Learning Systems&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers don’t have a notion of the world around them. Nevertheless, the current generation of personal devices already attempts to hide that fact by providing context-specific information and recommendations that are based on some interpretation of previous input (e.g. search terms) and behaviour (e.g. commute patterns). At this stage, most users don’t expect websites, mobile phones or tablets to give useful predictive insight. True-positive predictions (&lt;em&gt;‘I see you’re arriving at the cinema - would you like to see a list of movies?’&lt;/em&gt;) are often met with positive surprise, false-positive predictions (&lt;em&gt;‘Customers who bought this book about contraception als wanted to know about diapers’&lt;/em&gt;) provoke laughter. &lt;strong&gt;We usually expect to be disappointed and recommender systems to be broken - it’s the reality of machine learning UX.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the anticipated billions of devices that make up the Internet of Things, it becomes clear that information overload is imminent. We cannot longer digest the vast amount of raw data coming off these devices; i.e. from a practical as well as a UX perspective we have to get away from looking at raw output on dashboards (the proverbial ‘app for each device’) to intelligent systems that can deal with this data in real-time and provide users with agglomerated context-specific information and relevant, actionable insight. Add speech: Rather than having a nagging voice remind us every minute of an impending energy crisis, we only want to interrupt a journey if it is clear that it cannot be completed without refuelling the car, and that there is a reasonably opportunity to do so nearby. A well-trained machine learning method could be used to infer such ‘knowledge’ from a set of arbitrary data, based on statistical considerations and properties of previously learned data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A machine learning method may build a classifier that categorises combinations of incoming data (e.g. amount of gas, distance to target, distance to next gas station, etc) as belonging to groups (&lt;em&gt;‘this is a good opportunity for refuelling’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘this is not a good moment to annoy the driver’&lt;/em&gt;). Conceptually we can use the classifier at any time (even when it is not ‘trained’), but the initial state of any machine learning system is that of ignorance, i.e. it is unclear whether or not a a prediction is true and the decision may be random. While ‘on-the-fly’ learning exists, &lt;strong&gt;ultimately all machine learning is iterative and requires regular feedback&lt;/strong&gt; to clarify to the computer whether a given set of data really belongs to one or another group: &lt;strong&gt;this is the training phase that makes the classifier useful, and more training and more feedback means better classifiers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In academic machine learning method development, as well as in applications of machine learning in the industrial R&amp;amp;D context, training is a widely accepted, necessary evil. &lt;strong&gt;Things become tricky when machine learning and the uninitiated consumer come together.&lt;/strong&gt; When a user without knowledge of the underlying process is confronted with repeated confirmation requests (&lt;em&gt;‘Do you agree this is a good moment to stop?’&lt;/em&gt;), &lt;strong&gt;the training phase can become a UX nightmare&lt;/strong&gt; that in the worst case makes the user avoid the system altogether, before it ever can become any good. We are already seeing websites and apps that use iterative training. Some take the confirmation strategy, but don’t communicate why they’re doing it. Others present even objectively bad predictions but allow the user to mark and discard these. Is voice control in respect to providing feedback to machine learning systems more or less intrusive? It seems that systematic A/B testing is required, as some communities (e.g. home automation geeks vs. professional truck drivers) may be more appealed by one or the other strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While providing a metric of the reliability of a prediction is a must for engineers, &lt;strong&gt;confronting consumers with p-values, false discovery rates or area-under-the-curve is a clear no go.&lt;/strong&gt; What is the best strategy to go about it? People of a certain age will remember how any weather forecast longer than a day into the future was just a random guess, and accepted the very fact. Nowadays, some weather websites feature a reliability score. But if an arbitrary ‘34% reliability’ provide more ‘actionable insight’ than the sheer acceptance that predictions are random is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can we avoid all this trouble by creating vast training facilities for machine learning algorithms in connected products? Likely not.&lt;/strong&gt; Good machine learning requires lots of training data. Power comes with large numbers. However, most predictions for the Internet of Things are going to be based on the integration of data across different devices. As everyone might have a different combination of devices that should be taken into consideration, and everyone might have a different scope for using the Internet of Things (the &lt;em&gt;‘What does our user want?’&lt;/em&gt; – think security, fitness, efficiency), providers of machine learning solutions cannot train their methods without the users themselves. We may want to think about large-scale simulations that draw bootstrapped ensembles of virtual devices and try to infer ‘this particular virtual user’s need’, but ultimately this will only lower the number of classes we’re trying to predict — if our features and classification itself are correct, that’s still subject to some sort of (human?) supervision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My personal conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt; Coming from the perspective of a machine learning method developer and having experienced bad UX around self-learning devices myself, I cannot provide solutions to the discourse but act as an interpreter between the fields.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thingslearn" /><category term="iot" /><category term="software" /><category term="analytics" /><summary type="html">A few months ago I submitted an abstract to a UX conference. I’m not sure if my proposal is going to be accepted, but I thought it would be worth sharing my thoughts on the user experience of Machine Learning Systems on my currently quite neglected blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">thingslearn goes Zühlke</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/09/18/thingslearn-goes-zuhlke.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thingslearn goes Zühlke" /><published>2016-09-18T09:52:57+02:00</published><updated>2016-09-18T09:52:57+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/09/18/thingslearn-goes-zuhlke</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/09/18/thingslearn-goes-zuhlke.html">&lt;p&gt;A few people who come to this blog know that I’ve been commercially active with &lt;strong&gt;thingslearn Ltd.&lt;/strong&gt; in the UK. The company served as a port-of-call for customers mostly in the &lt;strong&gt;IoT and M2M&lt;/strong&gt; arena, who were interested in the expert &lt;strong&gt;data science&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;machine learning&lt;/strong&gt; capability that my research group at the University of Cambridge had built up. I wrote before on my soon defunct academic group pages what IoT has to do with systems biology. A lot. In brief, complex biological systems share many properties with &lt;strong&gt;complex processes between interconnected technical systems&lt;/strong&gt;. On the abstraction level required for data science, the methods are identical. For a brief overview of the range of methods and tools we’ve developed, see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Daphne Ezer, Vicki Moignard, Bertie Gottgens, Boris Adryan
&lt;em&gt;PLoS Computational Biology 12(8), e1005072 (2016)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Determining Physical Mechanisms of Gene Expression Regulation from Single Cell Gene Expression Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Mathematical modelling based on vast amounts of numerical data of unclear distribution)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Chie Hosono, Ryo Matsuda, Boris Adryan, Christos Samakovlis &lt;em&gt;Nature Cell Biology 17, 1569–1576 (2015)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Transient junction anisotropies orient annular cell polarization in the Drosophila airway tubes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Network analysis)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lenka Skalska, Robert Stojnic, Jinghua Li, Bettina Fischer, Gustavo Cerda‐Moya, Hiroshi Sakai, Shahragim Tajbakhsh, Steven Russell, Boris Adryan, Sarah Bray
&lt;em&gt;The EMBO Journal 34, 1889-1904 (2015)&lt;/em&gt; 
&lt;strong&gt;Chromatin signatures at Notch‐regulated enhancers reveal large‐scale changes in H3K56ac upon activation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Markov-model based classification)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jin Hong, Robert Stojnic, Boris Adryan, Anil Ozdemir, Angelique Stathopoulos, Manfred Frasch
&lt;em&gt;PLoS Genetics 9(1), e1003195 (2013)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Genome-Wide Screens for In Vivo Tinman Binding Sites Identify Cardiac Enhancers with Diverse Functional Architectures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Machine learning with a large number of features from small classes)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Robert Stojnic, Audrey Fu, Boris Adryan
PLoS &lt;em&gt;Computational Biology 8(11), e1002725 (2013)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A graphical modelling approach to the dissection of highly correlated transcription factor binding site profiles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Learning from highly correlated features)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Radu Zabet, Boris Adryan
&lt;em&gt;Bioinformatics 28(11), 1517-24 (2012)&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A comprehensive computational model of facilitated diffusion in prokaryotes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(Understanding a system through agent-based simulation)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over the summer I’ve relocated to Germany, and joined &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zuehlke.com&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zühlke Engineering GmbH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in Eschborn near Frankfurt. Working with Zühlke is a great opportunity to leverage the exposure of a company that’s established and well-known in the European enterprise IT and industrial hard- and software solution market. What does this mean in practise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First and foremost: I can focus on the conversation between us -as solution providers- and customers who already know that they’re going to get a technically excellent solution. (Establishing that convo takes a lot more legwork if you’re a one-man show, and was just a waste of my time.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My skills are going to see a lot more use in a much wider area than I could have attracted as thingslearn Ltd. For obvious reasons I can’t be more specific, but in the first two weeks at Zühlke I have gained more insight into novel and exciting use cases of IoT analytics than in the previous two years doing thingslearn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;
If you, dear reader, are interested in an IoT/M2M solution and/or require consulting in any part of the IoT stack, including analytics, &lt;strong&gt;with Zühlke you’ve got a partner with a proven track record&lt;/strong&gt;. And yes, you can ask for me specifically. That’s an option. You can reach me on boris.adryan AT zuehlke.com.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thingslearn" /><category term="iot" /><category term="hardware" /><category term="software" /><summary type="html">A few people who come to this blog know that I’ve been commercially active with thingslearn Ltd. in the UK. The company served as a port-of-call for customers mostly in the IoT and M2M arena, who were interested in the expert data science and machine learning capability that my research group at the University of Cambridge had built up. I wrote before on my soon defunct academic group pages what IoT has to do with systems biology. A lot. In brief, complex biological systems share many properties with complex processes between interconnected technical systems. On the abstraction level required for data science, the methods are identical. For a brief overview of the range of methods and tools we’ve developed, see:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Business focus of IoT companies</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/07/15/business-focus-of-iot-companies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Business focus of IoT companies" /><published>2016-07-15T14:13:19+02:00</published><updated>2016-07-15T14:13:19+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/07/15/business-focus-of-iot-companies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/07/15/business-focus-of-iot-companies.html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past year I have worked extensively with a range of “IoT companies” (and I explain those quotes later) that required my knowledge about the Internet of Things including &lt;strong&gt;hard- and software development&lt;/strong&gt; and/or &lt;strong&gt;data analytics and machine learning&lt;/strong&gt;. These interactions came naturally, and my involvement was typically an obvious next step when my partners were lacking that skill set or experienced staff in their teams. While my work and contracts could be described as strictly B2B and I’m glad I’ve never had to do hardcore business development like cold calling potential customers, I was often doing work for particular external clients and projects. These clients didn’t care, in fact, in most cases I think they were happy to have dealings only with one company and not with an entire host of subcontractors. In a way, the companies I worked with could be described as &lt;strong&gt;systems integrators&lt;/strong&gt;, although none of them would actually describe themselves as such.
&lt;br /&gt;
The more I begin to understand how business works (remember, I have a 50% academic + 50% engineering mindset, plus a big mouth), the more I realise two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friend &amp;amp; Foe in business is gone.&lt;/strong&gt; This is probably pretty obvious in a time when Apple sues Samsung over mobile phone patents, while at the same time Samsung is involved in producing iPhone parts… It is the same in the IoT: While some companies are direct competitors for the parts of the cake, they may be customers of each other for other parts and may even have to collaborate on joint projects. This convolution is getting more complex every day, as most&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT companies are systems integrators.&lt;/strong&gt; This may be in contrast to the title that speaks of “focus”, but let me explain. Complete IoT solutions that address a particular need often feature bespoke hardware components including embedded code, off-the-shelf communication devices such as gateways, a data platform and backend software running in the cloud, as well as data processing and/or visualisation capabilities. Imagine your company is absolutely brilliant in doing one of those things, but has little expertise in the others? Well, it’s simple. You don’t sell. In fact, most clients getting started in the IoT will ask for a proof-of-concept, and I can assure you there are shrieks of terror when you’re a software startup and need to provide a hardware prototype to demonstrate the capabilities of your algorithms with just two months notice. At that stage, your business model suddenly shifts from selling good software to organising solutions that require you to understand and decide on things which are completely out of your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For that reason, there is pressure on IoT companies to collaborate. I’m not talking about gigantic pick+shovel manufacturers in this gold rush, the likes of Amazon AWS or Microsoft Azure. I’m talking about &lt;em&gt;normal companies&lt;/em&gt; trying to pay the bills by selling IoT directly to those who need it, be it hardware, software or services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As far as I can see it, there are currently &lt;strong&gt;three prevalent models to sell IoT solutions&lt;/strong&gt; to industrial clients:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consultancy services&lt;/strong&gt; that are totally agnostic to the technology they’re recommending. They explain why IoT is good and make a business case. They make their money based on (hopefully) good technical decisions, and one might think they’re providing objective information, as they’re going to be paid no matter which vendor the client ultimately decides for.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Specialised start-ups&lt;/strong&gt;, which are probably top-of-the-line for their particular niche and that have to stretch a bit to meet the demands of clients. Much like the consultants, they should be providing good information on the bits that complement their products, that make their product look good as part of a complete IoT solution. (This also explains the earlier quotes around “IoT company”: If you’re doing sensors, you’re not automatically doing IoT, but to sell them you may have to become an IoT company)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Full-stack providers&lt;/strong&gt; are companies that offer bespoke solutions for most industries. These are typically larger and established companies that can easily draw on existing internal resources and that have teams of hardware and software developers. From what I’ve seen, many clients would love to work with a full-stack provider, but fear the cost of the big names in the field and therefore favour interactions with smaller companies and start-ups.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this latter scenario gives rise to good opportunities. In fact, it’s already happening. Many well-established companies are indeed willing and able to accommodate external solutions if they appear better suited. For example, most players that are involved in the industrial IoT now also offer their own IoT cloud solution, but everyone knows that companies like Bosch and Zühlke offer integration e.g. with the Thingworx IoT Platform or EVRYTHING if it is the right thing to do. On the other side I’ve seen more than one occasion when OpenSensors was approached by customers to provide an all-encompassing solution, but it remained a big question mark whether a bigger partner would even be interested developing some bespoke hardware in collaboration. This is where both sides need to communicate better their willingness to interact.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaboration is key to interoperability.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Interoperability is key to collaboration.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that this level of collaboration and interaction is healthy for the development of IoT as a field and a win for everyone involved. The IoT can only live up to its promise if we stop treating the Internet as a replacement for a wire; i.e. if we can provide data integration across devices, companies and entire verticals. A rich ecosystem of data platforms, a choice of different gateways and devices that can speak to each other, and vendors that are not afraid of recommending competitor products in cases where their own product is not the best solution are key to breaking up silo thinking and pushing for interoperability. If we as a field get this right, I think everyone will benefit from the mix and match of IoT products.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rather than selling only complete end-to-end solutions, the market for mix and match must be infinitely larger.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only because of initial sales, but because clients are much more inclined to experiment and replace components of their IoT solution if things “just work”. Thus, we must not only look good to our clients, but also to our competitors that may choose to interact with us in their next project. And, as a start, that “looking good” can be done through adhering to open standards on the technical level, and fairness on a business level.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><summary type="html">Over the past year I have worked extensively with a range of “IoT companies” (and I explain those quotes later) that required my knowledge about the Internet of Things including hard- and software development and/or data analytics and machine learning. These interactions came naturally, and my involvement was typically an obvious next step when my partners were lacking that skill set or experienced staff in their teams. While my work and contracts could be described as strictly B2B and I’m glad I’ve never had to do hardcore business development like cold calling potential customers, I was often doing work for particular external clients and projects. These clients didn’t care, in fact, in most cases I think they were happy to have dealings only with one company and not with an entire host of subcontractors. In a way, the companies I worked with could be described as systems integrators, although none of them would actually describe themselves as such. The more I begin to understand how business works (remember, I have a 50% academic + 50% engineering mindset, plus a big mouth), the more I realise two things:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">IoT book review</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/07/06/iot-book-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="IoT book review" /><published>2016-07-06T09:42:44+02:00</published><updated>2016-07-06T09:42:44+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/07/06/iot-book-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/07/06/iot-book-review.html">&lt;p&gt;In a field like IoT the most relevant news are delivered online. But books aren’t dead. Currently authoring an &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/06/22/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot-june-16.html&quot;&gt;IoT textbook&lt;/a&gt; myself, I’m occasionally buying the odd IoT book to see if my own writing is vastly redundant or to provide contextual glue between more specialised works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, I’m usually &lt;strong&gt;not buying “hands-on” books&lt;/strong&gt;, i.e. tutorials how to do things. The reason for that is simple: In IoT like many other technological fields, the tools aren’t static. By the time books go into print, the versions of programming languages, syntax of software libraries and APIs, and even hardware products they are recommending, are usually already outdated. Their overall recommendations might still be valid, but the latent feeling of &lt;em&gt;technical debt&lt;/em&gt; remains when you’re even remotely aware that there’s already something better out there. That’s probably a long-winded way of saying you’re typically &lt;strong&gt;better off asking Google for advice&lt;/strong&gt;, and there are a great many tutorials, code examples and videos out there that teach you how to do things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’m more into books that explain concepts or define new paradigms rather than take you on tours of mouse clicks. Here are a few I’ve acquired over the past two years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/07/books.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;McEwen &amp;amp; Cassimally: &lt;strong&gt;Designing the Internet of Things&lt;/strong&gt; (2014)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rose: &lt;strong&gt;Enchanted Objects&lt;/strong&gt; (2014)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rowland et al.: &lt;strong&gt;Designing Connected Products&lt;/strong&gt; (2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bates: &lt;strong&gt;thingalytics&lt;/strong&gt; (2015)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Guinard &amp;amp; Trifa: &lt;strong&gt;building the web of things&lt;/strong&gt; (2016)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jamthe: &lt;strong&gt;IoT Disruptions&lt;/strong&gt; (2015 - Kindle edition)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re all rather different in what they’re trying to achieve, so it doesn’t make sense to interpret whatever I’m writing as a ranking between them. Rather, I’m reflecting on what I liked and didn’t like, so you can make a decision for yourself.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Designing the Internet of Things&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book, with its own Twitter handle &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/aBookofThings&quot;&gt;@aBookofThings&lt;/a&gt;, has been one of the first books covering the IoT from a maker and innovator perspective. I have to admit when I first bought it, I didn’t like it. Most information seemed rather superficial and I couldn’t quite put my finger on who their target audience was. Being a technologist, I felt the book tried to explain to me what I’ve already known from &lt;em&gt;spending hours and hours on the web everyday&lt;/em&gt;… …hold on, that may be the point: if you’re just starting to explore the IoT and you don’t have a technology background, it probably makes sense to briefly mention keywords from the world of networking, say what an Arduino and its difference to a BeagleBone is, or how crowdfunding works. Would I buy it again? No. Would I give it to a friend to see what IoT is all about? Only if they’re not too geeky. Is it a waste of time? Definitely not. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/amcewen&quot;&gt;McEwen&lt;/a&gt; and Cassimally have quite a few anecdotes to tell from their first steps in IoT (like, when it wasn’t called IoT…), and there’s the occasional informative glimpse even for routiniers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enchanted Objects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been a lot of hype about this book (Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/enchanted_objs&quot;&gt;@enchanted_objs&lt;/a&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidrose&quot;&gt;David Rose&lt;/a&gt; is without a doubt a MIT Media Lab IoT Technology Entrepreneur Spin Doctor (but in a good way!). This book is the essence of a few years of academic and entrepreneurial work. The message of the book is quite simple: &lt;em&gt;Don’t stare at the glass slab&lt;/em&gt; - i.e. try to find alternatives to the phone screen for your connected product. There are dozens of ways Rose is explaining this approach and he defines &lt;em&gt;the paradigm of enchanted objects&lt;/em&gt; with many great examples how to go about the user experience challenges in IoT. The book is full of good narratives that drive this message home. It’s one I’ve read front to back in a day, and I absolutely recommend it to anyone who’s interested in IoT product design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing Connected Products&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Enchanted Objects is the planning board, Designing Connected Products by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/clurr&quot;&gt;Rowland&lt;/a&gt; is the battle field. This textbook for product designers opens with the smartest dedication of them all: to Rowland’s son “&lt;em&gt;who will never know an Internet without all the Things&lt;/em&gt;”. Over 15 chapters this book defines what the IoT is, how designing products with a network connection is different, how products need to gracefully degrade and still be useful even if the server providing added value is no longer existent, etc etc etc. It’s all about making a connected product useful and pleasant, which in turn makes the upfront work by the designer a whole lot harder. As Rowland and co-authors draw on years of experience in the real world, the book does not provide recipes but exemplifies a lot on existing products. It is also definitely worthwhile to just flick through the book and have a look at the figures - the view guided by a designer reveal more than what usually meets the eye of an amateur. Designing Connected Products is probably the most expensive book in my collection (RRP $49.99), but at 700 pages it teaches a lot of background information and delivers concrete recommendations how to go about IoT product design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;thingalytics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drjohnbates&quot;&gt;Bates&lt;/a&gt; likes puns, as one can also tell by the title of his follow-up book: &lt;em&gt;thinganomics&lt;/em&gt;. If you are somebody who has to sell the value of data (to a customer, to a boss), this might be your book. It’s brief, it’s neatly typeset, punchlines are highlighted and there are plenty of URLs that substantiate the claims. A lot of it is based on concrete examples. Read it on the flight to your board meeting, and you’re all set. It also comes with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingalyticsbook.com&quot;&gt;nice website&lt;/a&gt;, containing some up-to-date information on IoT. However, the subtitle “Smart Big Data Analytics for IoT” is slightly misleading, or at least, I don’t see how the examples in the book are any smarter or the bigger from an analytical perspective than what any IoT data analytics person would do. Also, don’t expect technical details in this book. It’s all about the possibilities to save money through analytics, mostly in a M2M context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;building the web of things&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WoTbook&quot;&gt;@WoTbook&lt;/a&gt;) is interesting, because at first, I didn’t know what to make of it. Writing a book to push your company profile is a strategy I’ve seen with &lt;em&gt;thingalytics&lt;/em&gt;. The book has multiple parts and shows a considerable amount of node.js code as well as hardware examples using a Raspberry Pi. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/domguinard&quot;&gt;Guinard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vladounet&quot;&gt;Trifa&lt;/a&gt; are founders of an IoT platform and do use &lt;em&gt;that platform&lt;/em&gt; quite a bit in hands-on examples. However, this book also aims to teach some basic IoT principles and the reader gets to learn about network topologies, IoT protocols like MQTT and CoAP, or Internet security. But most importantly, they’re trying to establish a paradigm which they refer to as ‘web of things’ - an IoT in which interoperability is a solved problem. It’s especially this part where I see the biggest value of the book. If you’re entering IoT as a programmer and ‘service technician’, your company may have a silo attitude in which things do not collaborate. The book aims to change that view. The web of things concept shows how IoT as an ecosystem of discoverable and interoperable things might work. Would I buy this book again? Maybe not (well, I would, because Dom is a very likeable guy!). Would I recommend it as a first start? Yes, to somebody who prefers a well-structured printed book over a bunch of web tutorials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT Disruptions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sujamthe&quot;&gt;Jamthe&lt;/a&gt; is a brainstorming brought to paper. I got it on Amazon for £2, which is just about what I’d be willing to pay for a random list of IoT examples. I think it suffers from the same issues as &lt;em&gt;Designing the Internet of Things&lt;/em&gt;: It doesn’t go very deep, it’s not very systematically compiled nor comprehensive. Unfortunately, the McEwen book has some 320 pages and gets around to mentioning quite a few things, whereas this one is also short. It’s not wrong(!), but every single chapter left me with with an “…aaaaaaand?”. Maybe if you’re absolutely new to the field, that sort of cursory overview is useful, but if you haven’t spent your time under a technological rock in the past years, you’re likely in for a disappointment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">In a field like IoT the most relevant news are delivered online. But books aren’t dead. Currently authoring an IoT textbook myself, I’m occasionally buying the odd IoT book to see if my own writing is vastly redundant or to provide contextual glue between more specialised works.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Update: Higher education in the time of IoT (June ‘16)</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/06/22/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot-june-16.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update: Higher education in the time of IoT (June '16)" /><published>2016-06-22T15:25:12+02:00</published><updated>2016-06-22T15:25:12+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/06/22/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot-june-16</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/06/22/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot-june-16.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m sorry. It’s become quiet on my blog. The reason is that book writing has become my full-time occupation and is going to be all along until I’m joining &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zuehlke.com/ch/en/&quot;&gt;Zühlke Engineering&lt;/a&gt; for all things IoT and data science in September 2016. And believe me: after writing about IoT all day long, the last thing on my mind is writing even more about IoT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is just a brief update on what’s been happening in regards to the &lt;strong&gt;IoT book&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve alluded to a few times (see my rationale why we need a dedicated &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/12/14/higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot.html&quot;&gt;book for teaching IoT at university level&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/02/19/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot.html&quot;&gt;brief update&lt;/a&gt; after the first part had been written).
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thus, the state of play is now:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We got a publisher.&lt;/strong&gt; I had been contacted by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.artechhouse.com/International/Home.aspx&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Artech House&lt;/strong&gt; (UK)&lt;/a&gt; if I wanted to write a book about data and information models in IoT. This request was in direct response to my various materials on this blog about &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/02/16/four-branches-for-an-iot-ontology.html&quot;&gt;ontologies in the IoT&lt;/a&gt; and my experiments with &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/03/11/hands-on-with-vorto-iot-information-models.html&quot;&gt;Eclipse Vorto&lt;/a&gt;. I told them that these topics would be a part of &lt;em&gt;a book I’m currently writing&lt;/em&gt;, although a very small one. I’ve immediately had their attention and in contrast to the tedious dealings with some established academic publishers, the paperwork was a matter of a few weeks and the contract just needs signing (…which I haven’t done so far to keep writing fun). I’ve been told it’s no laughing matter, although I frequently make fun of them as one of their flagship publication is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.microwavejournal.com&quot;&gt;Microwave Journal&lt;/a&gt;, but they are a very IT, EE and RF heavy publisher.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I got co-authors.&lt;/strong&gt; Imagine you ask your 1,500 strong followership for assistance online and everyone just ignores you, but then in real-life over beer you mention &lt;em&gt;a book I’m currently writing&lt;/em&gt;, and it’s actually happening. My nagging skills have ultimately been successful and I’ve secured &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dobermai&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dominik Obermaier&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hivemq.com&quot;&gt;HiveMQ&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hivemq.com&quot;&gt;DC-Square&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/pzfreo&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paul Fremantle&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://wso2.com&quot;&gt;WSO2&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.port.ac.uk/school-of-computing/staff/mr-paul-fremantle.html&quot;&gt;University of Portsmouth&lt;/a&gt; as co-authors. Many practitioners know Dominik for his excellent series of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hivemq.com/blog/mqtt-essentials/&quot;&gt;blog posts about MQTT&lt;/a&gt;, and he is taken charge of Internet messaging and backend pains in the Software chapter of the book. Paul is the co-founder and CTO of WSO2, but at the moment is also doing a PhD in security and access management in the IoT: Who would be better suited to write that chapter? :-)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We’ve made progress.&lt;/strong&gt; Since the &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/02/19/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot.html&quot;&gt;last update&lt;/a&gt; in February I’ve finished the chapters on the history of the Internet and IoT, IoT applications and IoT/M2M architectures. Including the first chapter on physics and computing, that’s about 40,000 words and nearly 60 figures. About half of the hardware chapter is drafted, and over the next few weeks the first chapters will see some polishing so that they can go out to our external reviewers. I’m confident that the book is going to hit the stores in early 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most importantly, we have a title, as suggested by the publisher: &lt;strong&gt;Technical Foundations of the Internet of Things&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">I’m sorry. It’s become quiet on my blog. The reason is that book writing has become my full-time occupation and is going to be all along until I’m joining Zühlke Engineering for all things IoT and data science in September 2016. And believe me: after writing about IoT all day long, the last thing on my mind is writing even more about IoT…</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A user perspective on Eclipse IoT</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/04/02/a-user-perspective-on-eclipse-iot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A user perspective on Eclipse IoT" /><published>2016-04-02T12:01:43+02:00</published><updated>2016-04-02T12:01:43+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/04/02/a-user-perspective-on-eclipse-iot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/04/02/a-user-perspective-on-eclipse-iot.html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I spoke at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.meetup.com/London-Eclipse-User-Group/&quot;&gt;Eclipse User Group&lt;/a&gt; in London about the offerings the Eclipse Foundation has around open source IoT software. It was an interesting event with a very diverse set of speakers, ranging from geographic information systems to edu-tech and open source advocacy. Organizer &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tracymiranda&quot;&gt;Tracy Miranda&lt;/a&gt; wrote up a very nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://kichwacoders.com/2016/03/24/eclipse-converge/&quot;&gt;summary of the &lt;strong&gt;#eclipseldn&lt;/strong&gt; event on her website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the organisational lead of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/IanSkerrett&quot;&gt;Ian Skerrett&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kartben&quot;&gt;Benjamin Cabé&lt;/a&gt;, one of the seven main working groups is &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://iot.eclipse.org&quot;&gt;Eclipse IoT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This is probably a good moment to explain to the uninitiated reader that &lt;em&gt;Eclipse&lt;/em&gt; simply used to be an open source integrated development environment for Java (and still is: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eclipse.org/downloads/&quot;&gt;download the IDE&lt;/a&gt;), but over the past almost fifteen years has restructured into a foundation that works language-agnostic on a wide range of projects; very much like &lt;em&gt;Apache&lt;/em&gt; used to be a web server and now is a software foundation. Eclipse IoT is an umbrella project that coordinates the work of developers that are primarily based at a dozen companies with an interested in IoT or M2M. Amongst those are major players such as IBM, Bosch and Siemens, but also smaller companies that work in particular corners of the IoT, like dc-square and openHAB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set out to give an overview when and where particular Eclipse IoT projects can help to build IoT solutions. While it’s possible to find all that information in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://iot.eclipse.org/projects&quot;&gt;table on the Eclipse website&lt;/a&gt;, it can be daunting if you’re just getting started on an IoT project to understand what you need and where it fits. Good time to let my artistic streak come through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/04/slide4.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One can think about the various Eclipse IoT projects in terms of &lt;strong&gt;ecosystems, standards and components&lt;/strong&gt;. On the ecosystem level, Eclipse acts as integrator for projects that are required to build a complete end-to-end solution, starting from embedded code on microcontrollers to message brokers on gateways to backend software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I demonstrated one possible scenario how the &lt;strong&gt;ecosystem&lt;/strong&gt; bit helps designing M2M/IoT using this schematic around end device management:
&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/04/slide6.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eclipse.org/vorto/index.html&quot;&gt;Vorto&lt;/a&gt; GUI allows one to provide language-independent descriptions of devices, which via the Vorto code generators can be conveniently translated into objects/classes in any programming language for which such generator exists. (See my &lt;a href=&quot;/2016/03/11/hands-on-with-vorto-iot-information-models.html&quot;&gt;recent blog post about Vorto&lt;/a&gt;). On a very abstract level, a programmer could refer to “the radio” and “send x bytes” in their code, an interface presented by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.eclipse.org/proposals/edje&quot;&gt;EDJE&lt;/a&gt; hardware abstraction layer that takes care of the technical differences between various devices. Once developed, one can deploy the new code via &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.eclipse.org/proposals/hawkbit&quot;&gt;hawkBIT&lt;/a&gt; to a large number of devices at once. As such, hawkBIT reminds me of resin.io, which I &lt;a href=&quot;/2015/09/14/deploying-raspberry-pi-images-at-scale.markdown&quot;&gt;wrote about earlier&lt;/a&gt;. On the device itself then, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://projects.eclipse.org/projects/rt.concierge&quot;&gt;Concierge&lt;/a&gt; system is a small footprint Java core that would run that code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On the &lt;strong&gt;component level&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eclipse.org/kura/&quot;&gt;Eclipse Kura&lt;/a&gt; deserves a very honourable mention in the very long list of projects that can simply be deployed in one own’s IoT solutions. Kura is an easy-to-use gateway system that acts between sensor devices and a backend. Traditionally used for demonstrations on a Raspberry Pi, Kura and Pi now almost always go together, with e.g. the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openhab.org&quot;&gt;openHAB&lt;/a&gt; being widely used by hobbyists for home automation on the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While it is always possible to drill into the actual code of Eclipse projects (open source, &lt;em&gt;sic!&lt;/em&gt;), both on the ecosystem and the component level one doesn’t necessarily have to engage with the nitty-gritty of the underlying code. However, as Eclipse IoT also embraces important &lt;strong&gt;standards&lt;/strong&gt;, their libraries for M2M/IoT device communication via MQTT or CoAP are extremely powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/04/slide5.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my presentation I focussed on the explanation of MQTT as a very common protocol to send information from devices to gateways to servers. While the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mosquitto.org&quot;&gt;Mosquitto broker&lt;/a&gt; (another ‘component’) takes care of all of the message handling, the programmer only needs to memorise a few lines of syntax of e.g. the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eclipse.org/paho/&quot;&gt;Paho library&lt;/a&gt; to connect to the broker or react to particular MQTT topics via callback functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
I concluded my talk with a wishlist for Eclipse IoT: We need a project for data analytics and visual data representation. However, I had missed that the Eclipse had just embraced the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openanalytics.eu/architect&quot;&gt;Open Analytics project&lt;/a&gt; a few days earlier… The complete slides are available on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan/eclipse-iot-ecosystem&quot;&gt;SlideShare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><category term="software" /><summary type="html">A few weeks ago I spoke at the Eclipse User Group in London about the offerings the Eclipse Foundation has around open source IoT software. It was an interesting event with a very diverse set of speakers, ranging from geographic information systems to edu-tech and open source advocacy. Organizer Tracy Miranda wrote up a very nice summary of the #eclipseldn event on her website.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hands-on with Vorto IoT information models</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/03/11/hands-on-with-vorto-iot-information-models.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hands-on with Vorto IoT information models" /><published>2016-03-11T17:38:35+01:00</published><updated>2016-03-11T17:38:35+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/03/11/hands-on-with-vorto-iot-information-models</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/03/11/hands-on-with-vorto-iot-information-models.html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I attended the Bosch Connected Experience (BCX) 2016, an event co-organised by the lovely &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.designswarm.com&quot;&gt;Alex Deschamps-Sonsino&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thewavingcat.com&quot;&gt;Peter Bihr&lt;/a&gt; for IoT practitioners during the otherwise suit-heavy Bosch Connected World week. It was a first of its kind and I was curious what could be done at a hack event that aimed to mix tinkerers, students and SME-type IoT specialists with Bosch engineers and their industrial kit. And yes, the Bosch PR machinery was full on, as you can tell by below video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/vXq5QLyfMok&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a previous blog post I wrote about the use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://iot.ghost.io/four-branches-for-an-iot-ontology/&quot;&gt;ontologies in the IoT&lt;/a&gt;. An ontology establishes the relationships of objects to each other. The annotation of the objects, along with a link to an ontology, occurs in a &lt;strong&gt;data or information model&lt;/strong&gt; for the object. This can be all rather abstract and subject to mostly academic research. However, a few implementations have lately emerged for the IoT, with the promise of greater interoperability between Internet-connected devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s been a massive push in the UK to annotate devices with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hypercat.io&quot;&gt;Hypercat&lt;/a&gt; standard, allowing the exposure of devices in a catalogue along with brief annotations of their function. Unfortunately, it is difficult to find Hypercat services “in the wild”, i.e. the adoption of the standard is rather restricted to those who have joined the consortium. Quite promising, however, is a new project: For the past year or so the &lt;a href=&quot;http://iot.eclipse.org&quot;&gt;Eclipse IoT&lt;/a&gt; project &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eclipse.org/vorto/&quot;&gt;Vorto&lt;/a&gt; has been ongoing. It’s hosted by the Eclipse Foundation but provided with significant human resources by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bosch-si.com/home/homepage.php&quot;&gt;Bosch Software Innovations&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Vorto is a graphical user interface for the definition of IoT information models&lt;/strong&gt; (i.e. which data is associated with an Internet-connected device), but also comprises &lt;strong&gt;code generators&lt;/strong&gt; for a range of programming languages that translate the model into ready-to-use code objects. In contrast to the Hypercat consortium, the Eclipse Foundation very early into the project made &lt;strong&gt;sharing&lt;/strong&gt; an essential component of Vorto. There is now even a &lt;a href=&quot;http://vorto.eclipse.org/repo/#/&quot;&gt;public repository&lt;/a&gt; of IoT data models, although the BCX event revealed that there are a lot more models finished and already being used at Bosch than they care to share publicly…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/03/whattodowithVorto.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In brief, Vorto allows people to describe information models about their “thing” in a language-independent manner using the Vorto GUI. These models are then stored and made available in the Vorto repository. The Vorto code generator, an open design with a simple, extendable plugin-system, can take such an information model and convert it into a variety of different code representations, i.e. Python or Java classes. This has the big advantage that when adjustments to the data model are necessary, code changes are consistently translated to all languages. One example how Bosch uses the technology in-house is for the data (model) exchange with their cloud platform partner Thingworx. Bosch engineers define the data model for their products, Bosch software specialists use the model and the code to write applications, while the folk at Thingworx use a code generator specific to their platform. This way, both Bosch software and Thingworx implementation are guaranteed to match in terms of data model, minimising the effort to create complementary interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the hack-a-thon, I chose to work on a project that would bring Vorto and my favourite rapid prototyping tool &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nodered.org&quot;&gt;Node-RED&lt;/a&gt; together. As it is possible to query the Vorto model repository using a REST API, I had intended to write some &lt;strong&gt;JavaScript code that retrieves the model and on-the-fly converts it into a Node-RED node that can be deployed&lt;/strong&gt; straight away. Unfortunately, I had completely neglected the fact that while it’s simple to define the interface, a Node-RED node without access to the actual hardware is rather pointless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/03/team.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
The Team, left to right: Nico, Christoph and Boris.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, our team [&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BorisAdryan&quot;&gt;Boris Adryan&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adryan.de&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;), Christoph Brockmann and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/iNic0&quot;&gt;Nico Castelli&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiwi.uni-siegen.de/wirtschaftsinformatik/mitarbeiter/wmitarbeiter/castelli/&quot;&gt;web&lt;/a&gt;)] devised a strategy as follows: Using the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eclipse.org/vorto/documentation/developer-api/codegenerator-implementation.html&quot;&gt;plugin system for code generators&lt;/a&gt;, we wrote a &lt;strong&gt;native Vorto plugin for Node-RED&lt;/strong&gt;. On the way we’ve discovered a range of issues with undocumented dependencies and actual bugs, which we fed back to the Vorto team. With half of their staff being based in Singapore and their other half attending EclipseCon in the US, Twitter and Gitter were essential communication channels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/03/codegenerator.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Node-RED nodes are usually &lt;a href=&quot;http://nodered.org/docs/creating-nodes/first-node&quot;&gt;composed of two files&lt;/a&gt;: an HTML file that defines the look of the node, and a node.js file with the actual implementation. The Node-RED node code that is being generated by our code generator really only defines an interface to the Vorto definition. From the data model itself it is hard to infer which parameters should definitely be presented and which ones are less important. Hence, we opted for a GUI-less representation of the device and only the name of the node can be edited. All properties of the data model are auto-generated in the code and are accessible through the message object &lt;em&gt;msg&lt;/em&gt;. At appropriate sections in the code, we highlight where to include external libraries and write the code that ultimately interacts with the hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As code stubs and header files are entertaining only for the best of geeks, we collaborated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tamberg&quot;&gt;Thomas Amberg&lt;/a&gt; who had managed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/tamberg/boschhack/raw/tip/2016/HttpToOPService/http-to-op-service.js&quot;&gt;hack a Bosch Rexroth Nexo Nutrunner&lt;/a&gt; industrial screw tightening tool, for which we had a Vorto data model available. It took us indeed only &lt;strong&gt;a few minutes to integrate his code into the Node-RED node stub, and allow people to send tweets to the Nexo&lt;/strong&gt; hand tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;At the same time, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/tamberg&quot;&gt;@tamberg&lt;/a&gt; writes code to control a beastly industrial nut runner. See projects converge? &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcx16?src=hash&quot;&gt;#bcx16&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/wKW4Ehjj2t&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/wKW4Ehjj2t&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Boris Adryan (@BorisAdryan) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/BorisAdryan/status/707226906287017985&quot;&gt;March 8, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><category term="software" /><category term="node-red" /><summary type="html">Last week I attended the Bosch Connected Experience (BCX) 2016, an event co-organised by the lovely Alex Deschamps-Sonsino and Peter Bihr for IoT practitioners during the otherwise suit-heavy Bosch Connected World week. It was a first of its kind and I was curious what could be done at a hack event that aimed to mix tinkerers, students and SME-type IoT specialists with Bosch engineers and their industrial kit. And yes, the Bosch PR machinery was full on, as you can tell by below video.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Update: Higher education in the time of IoT</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/19/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Update: Higher education in the time of IoT" /><published>2016-02-19T11:43:46+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-19T11:43:46+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/02/19/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/19/update-higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot.html">&lt;p&gt;In November I’ve started &lt;a href=&quot;https://iot.ghost.io/higher-education-in-the-time-of-iot/&quot;&gt;thinking about teaching resources&lt;/a&gt; for IoT. My motivation is that IoT is a vast area covering hardware, software, security, data analytics, product design, and many more specialist fields that are all taught as standalone courses at the university level. However, as integrative and interdisciplinary thinking is of the essence for successful IoT products, I had been looking for a textbook that would allow IoT practitioners with a particular background to &lt;strong&gt;learn key concepts from &lt;em&gt;all other&lt;/em&gt; areas&lt;/strong&gt;. I’m convinced that people with broad knowledge have better ideas and out-of-the-box thinking abilities, and thus I’d expect a software specialist to know basic ideas of product design, a security researcher to understand the nature of electric current, or a hardware engineer to be aware of the fallacies of distributed computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People have argued that books with titles along the lines of “&lt;em&gt;[random technology, hardware platform, programming language] for IoT&lt;/em&gt;” are by far more relevant for practitioners, but I take the stance that albeit many computer scientists ultimately are employed as programmers, their academic education is going to cover many subjects of computer science, not just programming - for a good reason. And the same should apply for the future generation of IoT engineers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My proposed &lt;strong&gt;book outline&lt;/strong&gt; covers the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Principles and Information Theory&lt;/strong&gt; The physics, electronics and engineering required to understand IT and communications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internet&lt;/strong&gt; A historical perspective from networks to hypertext to Web 2.0 to connecting hardware.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applications of M2M and IoT&lt;/strong&gt; Showcases for M2M and IoT in important verticals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT Architectures&lt;/strong&gt; Network architectures, hub (or no hub), uni- or bi-directional, issues with UX and UI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware&lt;/strong&gt; Power options (including theory), actuators, sensors, embedded systems, communication.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software&lt;/strong&gt; Internet protocols, embedded software, backend software, data analytics, standardisation (interoperability, device catalogues, ontologies).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt; Attack surface, securing hardware, securing software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT, People and Society&lt;/strong&gt; societal changes, privacy, ethical considerations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current table of contents covers some 120 topics, so this is of course just a brief overview. At this stage it’s hard to tell how many pages the book is going to have (or if I’m ever going to finish it, given that I’m going to seek proper employment by summer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past two and a half months I have worked on the first chapter, Physical Principles and Information Theory. Some of my technical reviewers have already gotten back to me about the first 30 or so pages. It’s interesting that those who’ve read courses at German universities found it rather superficial, while most of my British friends thought it was too theoretical and very far away from what’s relevant for a practitioner. In a way, that confirms that I’m on the right track, as I’m thinking about my experience at the University of Cambridge and remember that I’ve often expressed my concern about their narrow undergraduate education. With my current degree of granularity and detail, I’d assume the first chapter to have about 60 pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still looking for co-authors who might be interested in particular sections of the book, or people with expert knowledge to validate my explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Postscriptum&lt;/em&gt;: From a practical perspective, I’ve found Scrivener a very useful tool to structure and draft my content and collate information from the interwebs. I’m using TeXPad to do the proper typesetting in LaTeX and EazyDraw to generate EPS figures (35 line art or gray scale figures). So far I’ve had to use two pictures, for which I managed to obtain permission to reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><category term="education" /><summary type="html">In November I’ve started thinking about teaching resources for IoT. My motivation is that IoT is a vast area covering hardware, software, security, data analytics, product design, and many more specialist fields that are all taught as standalone courses at the university level. However, as integrative and interdisciplinary thinking is of the essence for successful IoT products, I had been looking for a textbook that would allow IoT practitioners with a particular background to learn key concepts from all other areas. I’m convinced that people with broad knowledge have better ideas and out-of-the-box thinking abilities, and thus I’d expect a software specialist to know basic ideas of product design, a security researcher to understand the nature of electric current, or a hardware engineer to be aware of the fallacies of distributed computing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Four branches for an IoT ontology</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/16/four-branches-for-an-iot-ontology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Four branches for an IoT ontology" /><published>2016-02-16T10:18:34+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-16T10:18:34+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/02/16/four-branches-for-an-iot-ontology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/16/four-branches-for-an-iot-ontology.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iab.org&quot;&gt;Internet Architecture Board&lt;/a&gt; is holding a workshop on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Semantic Interoperability for the Internet of Things&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. They are seeking &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iab.org/activities/workshops/iotsi/&quot;&gt;position papers&lt;/a&gt; and participants for their workshop in March. Unfortunately, standardisation is not a revenue generating operation for my company &lt;a href=&quot;http://wwww.thingslearn.com&quot;&gt;thingslearn&lt;/a&gt; and a two-day trip to San Jose is therefore out of the question. However, I’ve discussed a few thoughts with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michaeljkoster&quot;&gt;Michael Koster&lt;/a&gt;, who is one of the organisers and who is going to talk about his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/connectIOT/HypermediaDemo/wiki/Overview&quot;&gt;Machine Hypermedia Toolkit&lt;/a&gt; and the principle behind HATEOAS (Hypermedia As The Engine Of Application State).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2014 I presented a talk on &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan/thing-monk-borisadryan2014&quot;&gt;ontologies for the IoT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; at thingmonk London, an annual IoT conference organised by developer analyst company &lt;a href=&quot;http://redmonk.com&quot;&gt;redmonk&lt;/a&gt;. During 2015 I refined my thoughts about the requirements for an IoT ontology and recorded a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oreilly.com/pub/e/3365&quot;&gt;webcast with O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt;. I recycled that presentation a few times during 2015 and spoke about the lack of interoperability between devices in the consumer IoT also at the Data Science London Meetup as well as the Open Data Science Community. The decks for these are also available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan&quot;&gt;Slideshare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the IAB call for papers as incentive to finally writeup my ideas about an IoT ontology, although very brief:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-from-biology-a-four-branch-ontology-for-the-internet-of-things&quot;&gt;Learning from Biology: A Four-Branch Ontology for The Internet of Things&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;abstract&quot;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this position paper we argue that ontologies and device annotation are essential resources to enable artificial intelligence and intelligent digital assistants for the Internet of Things. The biomedical research community has successfully established the Gene Ontology with the branches ‘Function’, ‘Process’ and ‘Localization’ to capture gene function. We propose that this tripartite framework is also suitable to define objects in the IoT, if it is complemented by a fourth sub-ontology that aims to capture human intuition: ‘Proxy and Avatar’. We conclude with organizational details and a recommendation for pragmatic choices in ontology design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In traditional machine-to-machine (M2M) communication there are usually well-defined workflows with concrete input, processing and output devices. An example for such M2M architecture would be an industrial control system with a set of sensors and actuators. However, in the emerging &lt;em&gt;consumer Internet of Things (IoT)&lt;/em&gt;, workflows will be dependent on each individual user, their interests, and their access to particular device combinations. Intelligent digital assistants will have to generate workflows dynamically and in real-time, based on user preferences and the capabilities of the available devices. A workflow for a user with an interest in home automation may control the heating system on the basis of room occupancy sensors, while a workflow for a user with an interest in health may depend on fitness and sleep tracking devices - and both workflows may require information from an outside thermometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of this thesis, we assume that an intelligent assistant has access to a reliable &lt;em&gt;device catalogue&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. it can obtain a truthful inventory of all IoT devices that are to the user’s disposition. However, in order to establish that there is a &lt;em&gt;conceptual link&lt;/em&gt; between the outside thermometer and smart heating and/or exercise, the decision making process needs to explicitly know about this relationship (i.e. that thermometer X is an outside thermometer, and that the temperature suggests that going for a run is an appropriate activity). This information can be captured in an &lt;em&gt;ontology&lt;/em&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;controlled vocabulary&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;defined relationships&lt;/em&gt; between the entities. Unfortunately, there is no general and widely used ontology for the IoT yet, with semantic interoperability being one of many issues in ontology development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than enumerating the various shortcomings of current draft ontologies (e.g. W3C Semantic Sensor Network Ontology), and/or existing data, information and object models (e.g. IPSO Smart Objects, Eclipse Vorto), in this thesis we want to propose that one single-branched ontology cannot effectively represent complex relationships, but that a multibranch approach as it is used in the Gene Ontology (GO) can capture relevant computable meta-information: The ‘what’, ‘where’ and ‘when’ of device utility. Importantly, our approach does not replace the existing technologies, but allows for their integration through cross-references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-from-gene-ontology&quot;&gt;Learning from Gene Ontology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the first complete genome sequences for eukaryotic organisms in the late 1990s, the computational biology community recognised the need for the systematic categorisation of gene function. The Gene Ontology Consortium agreed on three properties that are relevant to completely capture gene function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Function,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Process,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Localization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Function describes the chemical activity that a gene exerts, Process provides the context in which this Function is required, and Localization where the gene is required to participate in the Process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interest of brevity and scope the reader is referred to GO for biological examples. It suffices to say that GO is the defacto standard for biomedical functional annotation, with both academia and industry contributing to and using the resource heavily. At the time of writing, GO features over &lt;em&gt;40,000 unique *terms** in *three directed, acyclic graphs&lt;/em&gt; (reflecting the relationships ‘is a’,’part of’,’has part’ and ‘regulates’). They provide annotation from 100,000 scientific papers on more than 4 million genes across all phyla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fourth-branch-proxyavatar-for&quot;&gt;The Fourth Branch: Proxy/Avatar for&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The three branches of GO are sufficient to provide a factual representation of an object, be it of biological nature or a device in the IoT. For example, a thermometer inside a smart thermostat can be trialled for it’s utility in a home automation workflow by looking at its most granular annotation: Function: ‘measurement of ambient temperature’, ‘directly interacts with a control unit’; Process: ‘domestic temperature control’; Localization: ‘bedroom 1’. (The user-specific term ‘bedroom 1’ is a result of overloading the generic IoT ontology term ‘domestic’, see Figure).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/content/images/2016/02/exampleannot.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Figure:&lt;/strong&gt; Annotation of a connected thermometer with the three sub-ontologies Function, Process and Localization. The term ‘domestic’ would allow the injection of a user-specific sub-ontology ‘MY home’. This operation would only affect the user’s active copy of the ontology, not the official version. The necessary reannotation of devices with ‘domestic’ localization would only be possible for those owned by the user.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a meta-layer of information that is not as clear-cut and factual as Function, Process and Localization. It’s the the &lt;em&gt;Proxy&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Avatar&lt;/em&gt; function a device can have, and this is highly dependent on the individual user: Some cars are just cars, but your partner’s car in your driveway may be an indicator of their presence. The temperature sensor in your smart heating system can, under certain circumstances, be indicative of a fire. These are relationships that depend entirely on context and we anticipate a considerable amount of machine learning effort is going to be required to learn such context. The Proxy and Avatar sub-ontology would likely exist as a branch reflecting frequently inferred functions and processes, as well as a branch specific to the user which could be overloaded similar to the ‘domestic’ term in the example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ontology-building-and-annotation-logistics&quot;&gt;Ontology Building and Annotation Logistics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Gene Ontology with its currently 40,000 terms has been built over the past 17 years, entirely by human curation. The US NIH has contributed $44,616,906 from 2001-2014, a sum likely matched by European funding bodies. This currently pays for 100 professional curators worldwide with domain-specific knowledge who continuously update and grow the ontology, and annotate novel biological entities. The curators use computational tools to manipulate both the ontology and the annotations, however, it is a manual process. As knowledge grows, ontology terms are frequently redefined, refined or retired. The necessary retrofit to the annotated genes is, again, manual, albeit with the support of appropriate automation tools. Even though subject of extensive machine learning efforts, &lt;strong&gt;automatic ontology building&lt;/strong&gt; and gene annotation is widely considered experimental and &lt;strong&gt;not fit for production purposes&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Open Biomedical Ontologies Foundry currently knows 50+ domain-specific ontologies. Where appropriate, GO terms carry optional &lt;strong&gt;cross-references&lt;/strong&gt; to terms in those external ontologies. It is noteworthy that this mapping is usually the result of a manual process, as &lt;strong&gt;simple word-matching approaches have proven extremely unreliable&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the size of the ontology, GO offers lightweight annotation with a few specific terms, as the relationship types allow the backwards-inference of less concrete terms; e.g. a “thermocouple transition joint probe” over multiple “&lt;em&gt;is a&lt;/em&gt;” relationships indeed is a “thermometer”. However, the choice of ontology endpoint, degree of granularity and generality of terms has to be pragmatic. In one particular case, we established that the knowledge of 15 years of research yielded some 47 publications on a gene, which was work contributed by 100+ authors in 50+ PhD thesis. Nevertheless, the gene only has 15 direct annotations, giving rise to 150 inferred annotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When building an IoT ontology such pragmatism would allow the ontology to grow in small steps rather than exploding with each and every new device or device type. It would also allow community efforts and crowd-sourced activities for device annotation, as carefully balanced and more general terms are more easy to use (rather than vendor-specific fine-grained ones). Although there are going to be billions of connected devices in the future, many of these devices are going to be conceptually ‘the same’. Also, it is conceivable that the number of applications/workflows that users require is even smaller. It is therefore feasible to derive an ontology that caters well for all workflows without the need to annotate each device with the maximum number of fine-grained details. Certain meta-information as detailed in the Semantic Sensor Network Ontology (such as the survival range for a device), which is not relevant for the majority of workflows, would still be accessible through cross-references.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(in lieu of links in the document)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W3C Semantic Network Ontology
[https://www.w3.org/2005/Incubator/ssn/ssnx/ssn]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IPSO Smart Objects
[http://www.ipso-alliance.org/ipso-community/resources/smart-objects-interoperability]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eclipse Vorto
[https://www.eclipse.org/vorto]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gene Ontology
[http://geneontology.org]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Open Biomedical Ontologies Foundry
[http://obofoundry.org]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizing the Internet of Things - O’Reilly Webcast
[http://www.oreilly.com/pub/e/3365]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides for: Organizing the Internet of Things
[http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan/oreilly-webcast-organizing-the-internet-of-things-actionable-insight-through-ontologies]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slides for: Ontologies for the IoT - London Data Science Meetup, 28 May 2015
[http://www.slideshare.net/BorisAdryan/data-science-london-meetup-280515]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="thingslearn" /><category term="iot" /><summary type="html">The Internet Architecture Board is holding a workshop on Semantic Interoperability for the Internet of Things. They are seeking position papers and participants for their workshop in March. Unfortunately, standardisation is not a revenue generating operation for my company thingslearn and a two-day trip to San Jose is therefore out of the question. However, I’ve discussed a few thoughts with Michael Koster, who is one of the organisers and who is going to talk about his Machine Hypermedia Toolkit and the principle behind HATEOAS (Hypermedia As The Engine Of Application State).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Musings about wearable technology</title><link href="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/09/musings-about-wearable-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Musings about wearable technology" /><published>2016-02-09T10:18:55+01:00</published><updated>2016-02-09T10:18:55+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4444/2016/02/09/musings-about-wearable-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4444/2016/02/09/musings-about-wearable-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;If there’s one application that’s nearly always mentioned along with the consumer Internet of Things, it’s wearables. Now what makes a wearable a wearable, in contrast to other technology that you can wear like your fancy Casio calculator watch from 1980? It’s the connection to the Internet, or better: the added value that the device provides when it is connected. Sure, any pedometer that informs the user about their performance with a small status indictor can be worn, but we would only call the incarnations that connect to a remote database with an attractive and informative web front-end a wearable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I’ve recently been asked to sit on a panel about wearable technology at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iottechexpo.com/europe/&quot;&gt;IoT Tech Expo Europe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Not that I’m an expert on that particular class of devices, but I think I seemed like a good fit with my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thingslearn.com&quot;&gt;data analytics&lt;/a&gt; background. The panel members were asked to think about the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do we expect wearables to interact with the world around us?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the benefits wearables will bring to society and businesses?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the difficulties in creating a real value proposition?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Making wearable technology a must have consumer good – how do we turn cool technology into something that makes a difference to people and organisations?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Examining the challenges for wearable technology – e.g. battery life, data collection, and functionality and what are the possible solutions?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can we overcome customer concerns with wearable data collection and ensure that received value makes the data sharing trade-off worthwhile?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are very broad questions, especially when projecting that the most innovative applications of wearables are still to come. And again, how do we define a wearable? Is David Rose’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://postscapes.com/ambient-umbrella&quot;&gt;Ambient Umbrella&lt;/a&gt; a wearable? If the definition is that it has to be attached to the user and not be carried: No. Is any sort of smart watch that communicates to a mobile phone one? Maybe. How do we draw the line to smart clothing, like connected sportswear? One of the clear-cut cases may be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sunsprite.com&quot;&gt;SunSprite&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;strong&gt;small device that can be tagged on to any clothing&lt;/strong&gt; to monitor sun exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, at this stage, most of these devices are still going to rely on some Bluetooth Low Energy (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bluetooth_low_energy&quot;&gt;BLE&lt;/a&gt;) communication to a mobile phone, such that &lt;strong&gt;edge computing and data transfer to the Internet is managed by ‘a hub device’&lt;/strong&gt; that most of us carry around anyway. This has the clear advantage of reduced size and increased battery life-time for the wearable device. In order to be useful when the phone isn’t around, most premium devices have indicator lights to communicate simple information even in the absence of a phone or the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s difficult to assess the &lt;strong&gt;societal benefit&lt;/strong&gt; of wearables. Think fitness trackers: We still lack systematic studies if they really make people more active, or if mostly active people purchase them. If it’s indeed the former, then one could probably estimate the reduced burden on health care systems etc. Unfortunately, it’s still too early to make such assessment. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://flic.io&quot;&gt;Flic button&lt;/a&gt; is a wireless button that can be attached to clothes (or anything else) to trigger actions on a mobile phone. Can we speak about a ‘societal benefit’ if crime victims can instantaneously call the police and transmit there whereabouts and probably a video feed to the authorities? In a world where everyone carries one, I’d call that ’societal’, but at this stage, that’s a no for me. However, think about the aggregated analysis of hundreds of Flic-triggered alarm calls: This could clearly help to identify crime hotspots and initiate preventive action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;benefits to businesses&lt;/strong&gt; are probably easier to identify, at least for the businesses themselves. Flic recently reported on a collaboration with a large pizza delivery chain. Add some sort of unique identifier to any wearable and their users, and they can be used for payments. Apple Pay and the ability to purchase your coffee with their smart watch is only the first step. Insurance companies are probably most interested in data from any wearable device: activity is only one indicator of health risk. Playing devil’s advocate, why not take environmental sensors into account to calculate someone’s score? If their client frequently is exposed to elevated levels of nitric oxide whilst roaming the streets of London, why not add a few pence to the cost of their contract? Google has recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techradar.com/news/wearables/google-s-smart-contact-lenses-just-went-from-concept-to-reality-1302370&quot;&gt;filed a patent&lt;/a&gt; for a contact lens that can monitor blood sugar levels. That’s going to be expensive for binge-eating diabetics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aforementioned examples obviously highlight the &lt;strong&gt;danger of ‘dual-use’ information&lt;/strong&gt;. Environmental monitoring with wearables could add a huge benefit for city councils (in aggregated form), but linking the information back to individuals might bring difficulties we haven’t even started to foresee. Have I mentioned that cigarette smoke could be quite easily identified…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a data analytics perspective the value proposition of all these scenarios is clear, but there will have to be incentives for people to buy and use some of these wearable devices. Would you be willing to pay a few hundred pounds for an environmental monitor if, except for informing yourself, you’re essentially providing a service to your local authorities and create a potential backdoor for insurance companies to deny you their protection? The only way this can happen is by &lt;strong&gt;convincing each and every user of the common good&lt;/strong&gt;, and how it is going to benefit them — but when has that ever worked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage &lt;strong&gt;I don’t think that there are too many technical issues&lt;/strong&gt; with wearable devices. At a time when we’re used to charging our mobile phones very much every day, the week-long lifetime of many devices is sufficient, the 18-hour cockup of the Apple Watch aside. Especially with BLE we’re already seeing greatly improved lifetimes, and energy harvesting through sunlight, Piezo-electric or wireless recharging are already state-of-the-art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great issue remains: &lt;strong&gt;What’s in it for me?&lt;/strong&gt; And is the data and services the devices provide interesting enough when the novelty effect has worn off? Geeks will be geeks and are likely to purchase anything with the ‘connected’ label. However, I’m wondering how many of the fitness trackers in the £10 price range are actually regularly worn? As with the entire consumer Internet of Things, I predict that we’re going to see a slow flooding of the market with cheap devices and that eventually, at some point, the integrative analysis of information is going to create a holistic digital view of our lives - if we want that. That’s a pervasive Internet of Things without any bells and whistles, something that’s just there, and that we can tap into if we wish.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="iot" /><summary type="html">If there’s one application that’s nearly always mentioned along with the consumer Internet of Things, it’s wearables. Now what makes a wearable a wearable, in contrast to other technology that you can wear like your fancy Casio calculator watch from 1980? It’s the connection to the Internet, or better: the added value that the device provides when it is connected. Sure, any pedometer that informs the user about their performance with a small status indictor can be worn, but we would only call the incarnations that connect to a remote database with an attractive and informative web front-end a wearable.</summary></entry></feed>